<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Newes from Flanders and Ostend a true declaration how the Lords States of the Vnited Prouinces, vnder the conduct of His Excellencie, haue set forth a princelike nauie of ships from Zeland, the 15. day of April 1604, which went to the island of Casant, where the foresayd Lords States haue taken in the sconce of Coxie, S. Catherine, S. Philip, and Isendiick, with other small sconces and holds / translated out of Dutch into English.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1604</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 14 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A00922</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11029.5</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S2126</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">23060509</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 23060509</idno>
            <idno type="VID">26159</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A00922)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 26159)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1796:4)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Newes from Flanders and Ostend a true declaration how the Lords States of the Vnited Prouinces, vnder the conduct of His Excellencie, haue set forth a princelike nauie of ships from Zeland, the 15. day of April 1604, which went to the island of Casant, where the foresayd Lords States haue taken in the sconce of Coxie, S. Catherine, S. Philip, and Isendiick, with other small sconces and holds / translated out of Dutch into English.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[12] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Arnold Hatfield for Iohn Bill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>[1604]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint date suggested by STC (2nd ed.).</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A⁴ B².</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Lambeth Palace Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Netherlands --  History --  Wars of Independence, 1556-1648.</term>
               <term>Flanders --  History.</term>
               <term>Belgium --  History --  1555-1648.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:26159:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 50 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:26159:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 50 -->
            <p>
               <hi>Newes from</hi> Flanders <hi>and</hi> Oſtend.</p>
            <p>A TRVE DECLARA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion how that the Lords States of <hi>the vnited Prouinces, vnder the</hi> conduct of his Excellencie, haue ſet forth a princelike Nauie of ſhips from <hi>Zeland,</hi> the 15. day of April 1604:</p>
            <p>Which went to the Iſland of <hi>Caſant,</hi> where the foreſayd Lords States haue taken in the Sconce of <hi>Coxie, S. Catherine, S. Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lip,</hi> and <hi>Iſendiick</hi> with other ſmall ſconces and holds.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Tranſlated out of Dutch into Engliſh.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>LONDON Printed by <hi>Arnold Hatfield</hi> for <hi>Iohn Bill.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:26159:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 51 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:26159:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 51 -->
            <head>To the Reader.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>Notwithſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the long (almoſt this three yeres) beſieging of the Towne of <hi>Oſtend;</hi> the Lords States of the vnited Prouinces, haue thought it good, to land an Armie in <hi>Flanders,</hi> hoping by that meanes to withdraw the ſiege from <hi>Oſtend:</hi> and perceiuing that the Enemie for all that leaues not the ſiege, but daily gets neere vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the ſame, hoping likewiſe to get it in, and ſo perſwading himſelfe, that nothing ſhall be able to withſtand his might, but all to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der his power; to that ende they of <hi>Flanders</hi> haue employed all their forces to bring vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the ſaid Towne of <hi>Oſtende,</hi> thinking by that meanes to haue all that Countrey ſo ſure vnto them, that none were able to ſet any more footing in that land, to winne any thing from them; not thinking ſo much on the Lords ſtrong hand (the other meanes) as of late he hath ſhewed, and is like to come to
<pb facs="tcp:26159:3"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 52 -->paſſe; when alwayes the Enemie thought (if <hi>Oſtend</hi> were won) not ſo much as a win<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow would be left open thorow which any man might by any meanes preiudice them. God notwithſtanding hath opened a doore to his Excellencie, to let him in; as we may ſee in reading of this briefe and true declarati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, for which we are highly to praiſe God, and to praie moreouer that his Excellencie (vnder the Lords protection) may haue a good proceeding in his godly purpoſe; and that it would pleaſe God to open the eies of the inhabitants of the land of <hi>Flanders,</hi> and others, which are vnder the Spaniards yoke, that we all may liue together in one true beliefe peace &amp; loue, to Gods glorie and our ſoules ſaluation.</p>
            <closer>Amen.</closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:26159:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 52 -->
            <head>
               <hi>A true declaration how that the</hi> Lords States of the vnited Prouinces, vnder the <hi>conduct of his Excellencie, hath ſet forth a Prince<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like</hi> nauie of ſhips from <hi>Zeland,</hi> the <hi>15.</hi> of April <hi>1604. which went to the Iſland of</hi> Caſant, <hi>where the</hi> foreſaid Lords States, haue taken in the Sconce of <hi>Coxie,</hi> S. Katherine, S. Philippe, and Iſendiicke, with other Sconces and holds.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Y the wiſe gouernment of the Lords States in gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall of the vntied Prouin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces in Netherland, and his Princelike Excellencie <hi>Maurice</hi> of <hi>Naſſaw,</hi> there were ſtaied and taken vp al about in the foreſaid vnt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Prouinces, a very great number of ſhips: and ſo furniſhed with all maner of warlike mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nition, to ſet forward towards the Enemies countrey; and hauing ſhipped all their horſe and foote, they came the <hi>13.</hi> of Aprill <hi>1604.</hi> before <hi>Zeland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>14.</hi> his Excellencie and the Lords States came before the Caſtle of <hi>Ramekins,</hi> where the foreſaid Nauie gathered them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelues together: Yet none of the Lordes States, nor his Excellencie, nor any other Lord, or principall man landed there, but re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mained all a ſhipboord; onely certaine Souldi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers went a ſhore to <hi>Middleborrow,</hi> and other
<pb facs="tcp:26159:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 53 -->places in the Iſland to bay ſuch things as they had néed of: which had warning in the euening towards eight of the clocke by the ſound of the drumme, that all Souldiers vpon paine of death, ſhould come a ſhipboord, and for that purpoſe were two of the gates of the ſaid citie all night left open to let them paſſe out. As the Souldiers were come aboord, you might heare about twelue of the clocke at night, thrée great péeces of Ordinances to be ſhot of, when the ſhips ſet ſaile together, with faire weather, and a ſoutheaſt winde, ſo that the foreſaid ſhippes and Souldiers came by breake of day before <hi>Swarte-gate</hi> and <hi>Kerken-gate,</hi> in the Iſland of <hi>Caſant,</hi> and there landed their men the <hi>15.</hi> of the moneth aforeſaid without the loſſe of anie one man.</p>
            <p>They that laie about and in the Sconce cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Swarte-gate,</hi> with other little holdes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>abouts, ran al away: whereupon his Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie marched forward toward the forte of <hi>Hofſteede,</hi> the which he alſo tooke in, and went forward to the Sconce <hi>Lippenen,</hi> ſo named of the Captaine that held the ſame, whom his Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie commanded to deliuer vp the ſaide Sconce; whoſe anſu ere was, that firſt he muſt ſée his Canon: whereupon his Excellencie ſent him word, that if he ſhould but ſhoote one ſhot thereat, he would take none of them to mercy, and foorthwith he placed two péeces, whereup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on they within preſently deliuered it vp, going
<pb facs="tcp:26159:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 53 -->out thereof with their weapons.</p>
            <p>The enemie hearing of his Excellencies ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proch, drew out foorthwith ſome part of their armie that lay before <hi>Oſtend,</hi> and came the <hi>15.</hi> day of the ſaide April on the weſt ſide of <hi>Sluis hauen.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>16.</hi> day the Enemy there began to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trench himſelfe with a halfe-moone, to ſtop the comming ouer of his Excellencie, who the <hi>17.</hi> and the <hi>18.</hi> of the ſame moneth ſtirred not, till he had fortified himſelfe in the Iland of <hi>Caſant,</hi> as the Enemy did on the Weſt ſide thereof: yet notwithſtanding his Excellencie brought one of his Batteries vnder the Caſtle of <hi>Sluis,</hi> where he cauſed certaine ſhot to be made on the Gal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies there, whereupon the Enemy cauſed them preſently to be brought vp higher to the Towne of <hi>Sluis.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>They of <hi>Sluis</hi> ſhot but little: His Excellen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie would looſe no time, but thought good to finde out another way to make his entrance in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the maine-land of <hi>Flanders,</hi> and is therefore in the night, the <hi>18.</hi> of Aprill aforeſaid, gone by land, but the next day returned to his Quarter.</p>
            <p>The night following, his Excellencie with a greater power goes forward, and takes in the Sconce of <hi>Coxie,</hi> and remained there the <hi>20.</hi> day. Then his horſe and foote make towards <hi>S. Catherines,</hi> and <hi>S. Phillip,</hi> where his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie brought all his power, and vpon their <hi>May day, <hi>ſtilo nouo</hi>
               </hi> (being <hi>Philip</hi> and <hi>Iacobs</hi> day)
<pb facs="tcp:26159:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 54 -->made more than an hundred great ſhot at the Sconce of <hi>S. Philip</hi> and <hi>S. Catherine,</hi> before eight of the clocke in the Euening, and the whole Leaguer the whole night ſo beſtirred themſelues, that they within fearing ſome ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall ſtorme, ran all away, and ſo his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie tooke in both the Sconces, to his great ioy and all his companie.</p>
            <p>Hauing now ſet firme footing in <hi>Flanders,</hi> he goes preſently to the Sconce of <hi>Iſendijcke,</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout which he entrencheth himſelfe, &amp; lodgeth his Armie ſo about it, ſhutting them ſo vp, that no man might either come foorth or goe in vnto them.</p>
            <p>The Enemie lyeth on the Weſt ſide of <hi>Sluis</hi> hauen, and cauſeth great ſtoore of Shallops from <hi>Bridges</hi> and <hi>Sluis</hi> to be brought, with two thouſand men in them, meaning to take in <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſant</hi> againe. Our men ſuffered the Enemie to land to the number of ſome thouſand, and ſo fell on them, and draue them to flight, which were the greateſt part of them Spaniards and Italians, crying out, <hi>A la barea, A la barca.</hi> Fiue of their ſhallops runne a ground and were drowned, with the men in them, the reſt ſlaine, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept ſeuentéene that were taken, whereof thrée were brought to his Excellencie. Beſides, our men got eight of the enemies Shallops.</p>
            <p>His Excellencie goes forward with <hi>Iſendijke,</hi> and in the night tooke one that ſalied out of the Sconce, who being examined, gaue to vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand,
<pb facs="tcp:26159:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 54 -->That there was want of all things, except ſhot and freſh water.</p>
            <p>His Exceliencie the <hi>29.</hi> of Aprill, ſent his Trumpet called <hi>Hans,</hi> to ſummon them to yéeld vp the Sconce; who at the ſecond ſound of the Trumpet, was ſhot in the head, of which he falles dead in the place. His, Excellencie hereat being very angry, ſent forthwith a drum to demand him that had ſhot his Trumpet, to be deliuered out vnto him, otherwiſe he would receiue none of them to mercy: wherupon they ſent out two Captaines, making excuſe that they by no meanes could learne who had done the ſame: yet notwithſtanding his Excellencie inſtantly demands that hee be deliuered before he will giue them any hearing, whereupon they returned to their Sconce; and in the Euening came to his Excellencie to parle about the deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery vp of the ſaid Scance, which giueth them no hearing. At laſt they come againe bringing with them him that had ſhot his Trumpetter, (which was an Italian) Then his Excellencie giues them the hearing, and are agréed on ſuch conditions as follow.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The Conditions.</head>
               <p>FIrſt, that they ſhall goe out of the ſaide Sconce, with their armes, without founde of drumme, and without their matches light.</p>
               <p>Secondly, that they ſhall leaue in the ſaide Sconce all their great Ordmance &amp; Munition.</p>
               <p>
                  <pb facs="tcp:26159:6"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 55 -->
Thirdly, that in <hi>4.</hi> moneths next following, they ſhall not beare Armes againſt his Excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lencie in <hi>Flanders.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, that his Excellencie will lende them ſhipping to carrie their ſicke and hurt men with their baggage to <hi>Sas,</hi> and for that ſhall two Captaines remaine in hoſtage with his Excellencie, till the foreſaid ſhippes come a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine.</p>
               <p>After this agréement, the Souldiers went out of the Sconce, the laſt of April, <hi>1604.</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout fiue of the clocke in the afternoone, being in number <hi>600.</hi> men.</p>
               <p>Since, it is crediblie reported by ſundrie paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers, that the <hi>2.</hi> of May, and the <hi>3.</hi> his Princely Excellencie marched vp toward the ruinated walled townes, <hi>Ardenborgh</hi> and <hi>Mid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dleborgh,</hi> and tooke them, and ſo marched vp to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward the Towne of <hi>Dam,</hi> diſtant a league from <hi>Bridges.</hi> Other Paſſengers comming fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <hi>Fluſhing</hi> the <hi>4.</hi> of May, ſay, that there were ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riued more Souldiers out of <hi>Frieſeland:</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe Switſers to be ſent to his Princely Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellencie in <hi>Flanders.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Alſo that the Countie or Earle <hi>Lodowicke</hi> of <hi>Naſſow,</hi> with other Captaines, with ſome <hi>14.</hi> Corronets of Horſemen, accompanied with the mutined Souldiers, called the Eſquadron, (ſtrong <hi>1500.</hi> horſemen, and <hi>800.</hi> footemen Muſkettiers) conducted by their <hi>Eletto,</hi> and di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected by Captaine <hi>Du Boys,</hi> for the States,
<pb facs="tcp:26159:6"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 55 -->are entred <hi>Brabant,</hi> with ſome Ordinance, and paſt vp by <hi>Bruſſel,</hi> to <hi>Mons</hi> in <hi>Henault,</hi> and as is reported, as farre as <hi>Buiſt,</hi> ſpotling all that they finde, ſaccaging all Abbeies, Townes, and Villages, Gentlemens houſes, that had no money to raunſome them, <hi>Wouere, Flerus</hi> and other townes burnt, ſéeking to bring al vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their contributions: but it is thought, they pretend to take and fortifie ſome Towne or place vpon the <hi>Mooſe,</hi> to ſtop all paſſage from <hi>Germanie</hi> and <hi>Italy.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Paſſengers comming from <hi>Fluſhing</hi> the fourth day of May, and others comming by the ſea-coaſt of <hi>Flanders</hi> and <hi>Oſtend,</hi> heard and ſaw on Saturday the fifth of this preſent Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, great ſhouting on all ſides at <hi>Oſtend,</hi> for the ſpace of ſeuen houres vpon the Seas, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aduenture to force them, before Prince <hi>Mau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rice</hi> campe came néerer. Great accuſations be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing made by Marques <hi>Spinola,</hi> the Generall before <hi>Oſtend,</hi> vnto the Archduke at <hi>Gant,</hi> of the Spaniſh Souldiers vntowardneſſe in fight, enuying the honour of the Italians and Walons, being maintained as is thought of <hi>Don Loys de Valaſco,</hi> and they vſe theſe words; <hi>Que non quieren mourir por vn Marques Spinola, mas ben por en Rey:</hi> which is, that they will not die for Marques <hi>Spinola,</hi> but will for their king: en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uying him the honor.</p>
               <p>It is like that they of the Countrey of <hi>Flan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> hauing contributed hetherto ſome ninetie
<pb facs="tcp:26159:7"/>
                  <!-- PDF PAGE 56 -->thouſand Guldens monthly, which is <hi>9000.</hi> pounds ſterling, for the maintenance of this ſiege, will now not be able to continue, being ſpoiled, and charged with thrée campes, the beſieging campe, and the Archdukes campe, and the Prince <hi>Maurice</hi> campe. Hitherto is all related what is paſt: beſée ching God to ſend a deliuerie to thoſe Prouinces, of Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh &amp; forreine gouernment, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by all Chriſtendome might come to a good peace, which God grant.</p>
               <closer>Amen:</closer>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
